<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Octopress | Mindthecode - Rambling about code]]></title>
  <link href="http://mindthecode.com/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mindthecode.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-02T13:30:36+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mindthecode.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stef van den Ham]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://mindthecode.com/blogging-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-26T11:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mindthecode.com/blogging-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As some of you may know, even though I don't blog all that often, I do mess about with it a lot. Mostly on what makes it run. Switching between <a href="http://croogo.org">Croogo</a>, a custom built <a href="http://cakephp.org">CakePHP</a> site, <a href="http://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> .. and back again.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For some reason none of them really seemed what I wanted. Croogo is cool enough, but actually adding posts is a hassle, and theming the thing was more of a puzle. Wordpress does the blogging thing really well, but it always feels ugly, and I had to rely on various plugins to make my post-flow work. I like writing in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>. There's a couple of Markdown plugins for Wordpress, but I would still have to copy paste stuff in webinterface, and had to hack it to allow for code-snippet sharing.</p>

<h3>Enter Octopress</h3>

<p>I somehow stumbled upon <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> earlier this week, and decided to give it a go. Short conclusion: <em>It's awesome</em>.</p>

<p>I won't go into all of the features, as that's nicely explained on their site, but basically it allows for this workflow:</p>

<ul>
<li>Run <code>rake preview</code> in the background</li>
<li>Write my posts in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>, with some settings in the top such as title, publish date, etc.</li>
<li>Hit save</li>
<li>See the changes in the browser</li>
<li>When happy, <code>rake deploy</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Now, the deploy function is very awesome. It automatically generate the site to a <code>public</code> folder, commits the whole thing to your git repository, and pushes it. When linked to a Github Pages site it will auto update your site.</p>

<p>So yeah, this is good stuff, as I can just write my plain text files like I want to, and without any further webinterfacing and option clicking I can publish new articles.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
